<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.7">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-11-19T21:07:33+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ice Cubes</title><subtitle>A Winter Blog</subtitle><entry><title type="html">How did PyCon Sweden go online?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/inspiration/pyconse/2020/11/15/organize-conference.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How did PyCon Sweden go online?" /><published>2020-11-15T14:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-11-15T14:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/inspiration/pyconse/2020/11/15/organize-conference</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/inspiration/pyconse/2020/11/15/organize-conference.html">&lt;h2&gt;Conferences in Times of Corona&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    The disruption in the event industry this year did also hit our organizing team at &lt;a href=&quot;www.pycon.se&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PyCon Sweden 2020&lt;/a&gt; .
    Last year we arranged our biggest conference until then. A two day conference with 3 keynotes, 17 talks,
    4 workshops and 2 panel discussions at a venue in the heart of Stockholm. For 2020 we had similar plans
    and then in March everything changed. Since the conference is usually planned for the fall, we had some
    buffer to decide if we even want to consider an on-site conference. We quickly decided against it and to
    go fully online instead. This didn't reduce the planning and we had new points to consider opening our registration
    up to the world.&lt;br&gt;
    With a lot of energy and will we extended
    &lt;a href=&quot;www.pycon.se&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PyCon Sweden 2020&lt;/a&gt; and arranged a 2 day conference with multiple tracks,
    4 keynotes, 35 talks, 4 workshops and 2 panel discussions!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Here is a checklist of things we had to do to arrange a conference of this format.
    One can invest more time in many of those points, like extended marketing, a remarkable state of the art webpage,
    intense participant &amp; sponsor engagement and high entertainment in general.&lt;br&gt;
    This checklist is not fully complete. Still it should allow you to arrange a conference with the main points covered.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    &lt;b&gt; 4 - 5 months before the conference:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;team&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;team&quot;&gt; Gather the team and set up regular meetings&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;notes&quot;&gt; Take notes during meetings, for example like
        &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/python-sverige/protokoll/blob/master/styrelsemote/boardmeeting-YYYY-MM-DD-template.md&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;date&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;date&quot;&gt; Decide a date&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;size&quot;
    &lt;label for=&quot;size&quot;&gt; Decide on the size (multiple tracks, 2 days)&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;platform&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;platform&quot;&gt; Test and decide on a streaming platform&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;keynotes&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;keynotes&quot;&gt; Invite Keynote speakers&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;webpage&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;webpage&quot;&gt; Setup a web page&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    &lt;b&gt; 2 - 3 months before the conference:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;cfpopen&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;cfpopen&quot;&gt; Open call for proposals&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;social&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;social&quot;&gt; Social media coverage, email ads&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;publish&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;publish&quot;&gt; Publish on social media reminders&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sponsors&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;sponsors&quot;&gt; Contact sponsors, sync expectations&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;keynote-announce&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;keynote-announce&quot;&gt; Keynote announcement&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;cfpclose&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;cfpclose&quot;&gt; Close CFP and decide on talks/workshops&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    &lt;b&gt; 1 month before the conference:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;team2&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;team2&quot;&gt; Increase meeting frequency&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;registrationopen&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;registrationopen&quot;&gt; Open registration&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;schedule&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;schedule&quot;&gt; Create schedule &amp; sync with speakers&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;talksetup&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;talksetup&quot;&gt; Set up broadcasts, background, links&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;webschedule&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;webschedule&quot;&gt; Publish schedule&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;engage&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;engage&quot;&gt; Set up participant engagement (give away, Slack)&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;publish4&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;publish4&quot;&gt; Publish on social media reminders&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    &lt;b&gt; 2 weeks before the conference:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;onboarding&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;onboarding&quot;&gt; Volunteer On-boarding&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;calendar&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;calendar&quot;&gt; Calendar reminders during conference in Slack&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;rehearsals&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;rehearsals&quot;&gt; Speakers Rehearsals&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;publish2&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;publish2&quot;&gt; Publish on social media reminders&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    &lt;b&gt; 1 week before the conference:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;moderation&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;moderation&quot;&gt; Prepare opening, closing and moderation&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;registrationclose&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;registrationclose&quot;&gt; Close Registration&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;prepare&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;prepare&quot;&gt; Prepare social media coverage during the conference&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;publish3&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;publish3&quot;&gt; Publish on social media reminders&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;feedbackprepare&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;feedbackprepare&quot;&gt; Design and prepare preliminary feedback form&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;communication&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;communication&quot;&gt; Clarify team communication and responsibilities&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    &lt;b&gt; Conference day:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;golive&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;golive&quot;&gt; Go live&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;havefun&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;havefun&quot;&gt; Have fun&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;slack&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;slack&quot;&gt; Create conversation/initiate engagement on Slack etc.&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;feedbackask&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;feedbackask&quot;&gt; Ask for feedback&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;debrief&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;debrief&quot;&gt; Debrief and celebrate&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    &lt;b&gt; 1 week after the conference:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;feedback&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;feedback&quot;&gt; Analyse feedback&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;retrospect&quot;&gt;
    &lt;label for=&quot;retrospect&quot;&gt; Retrospect and lessons learned&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Of course there are many more things that one could do during preparation time or the conference.
    And if there is not a lack of anything it is ideas.
    However keep in mind, that the time and energy you can spend on an event like this is
    highly dependent on the amount and availability of voluntarily work.&lt;br&gt;
    Since we want to keep our heads cool during the conference itself it is wise to prioritise and strike certain
    points out in order to give others enough attention. If things go terribly wrong and we are already at maximum
    capacity it could mean a total meltdown for some of us and would destroy our team dynamic drastically.
    &lt;br&gt;
    At PyCon Sweden we were incredibly lucky that we found committed volunteers that took full ownership to ensure a
    great experience both for the speakers and the audience. And I am thankful for each single contribution!
    &lt;br&gt;
    There are always some hick-ups here and there, especially with technic involved it usually doesn't get easier.
    A muted microphone, multiple posts with the same content, loss of connection up to a surrendering computer.&lt;br&gt;
    But honestly isn't exactly that the delightful and exciting part of a live conference?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    I hope you found the checklist usable and wish you good luck for your online event or conference!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    All the best, &lt;br&gt;
    Christine
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Conferences in Times of Corona The disruption in the event industry this year did also hit our organizing team at PyCon Sweden 2020 . Last year we arranged our biggest conference until then. A two day conference with 3 keynotes, 17 talks, 4 workshops and 2 panel discussions at a venue in the heart of Stockholm. For 2020 we had similar plans and then in March everything changed. Since the conference is usually planned for the fall, we had some buffer to decide if we even want to consider an on-site conference. We quickly decided against it and to go fully online instead. This didn't reduce the planning and we had new points to consider opening our registration up to the world. With a lot of energy and will we extended PyCon Sweden 2020 and arranged a 2 day conference with multiple tracks, 4 keynotes, 35 talks, 4 workshops and 2 panel discussions! Here is a checklist of things we had to do to arrange a conference of this format. One can invest more time in many of those points, like extended marketing, a remarkable state of the art webpage, intense participant &amp; sponsor engagement and high entertainment in general. This checklist is not fully complete. Still it should allow you to arrange a conference with the main points covered. 4 - 5 months before the conference: Gather the team and set up regular meetings Take notes during meetings, for example like this Decide a date Decide on the size (multiple tracks, 2 days) Test and decide on a streaming platform Invite Keynote speakers Setup a web page 2 - 3 months before the conference: Open call for proposals Social media coverage, email ads Publish on social media reminders Contact sponsors, sync expectations Keynote announcement Close CFP and decide on talks/workshops 1 month before the conference: Increase meeting frequency Open registration Create schedule &amp; sync with speakers Set up broadcasts, background, links Publish schedule Set up participant engagement (give away, Slack) Publish on social media reminders 2 weeks before the conference: Volunteer On-boarding Calendar reminders during conference in Slack Speakers Rehearsals Publish on social media reminders 1 week before the conference: Prepare opening, closing and moderation Close Registration Prepare social media coverage during the conference Publish on social media reminders Design and prepare preliminary feedback form Clarify team communication and responsibilities Conference day: Go live Have fun Create conversation/initiate engagement on Slack etc. Ask for feedback Debrief and celebrate</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An ice cube about how I became a PyLady?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/inspiration/pyladies/2020/11/01/becoming-a-pylady.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An ice cube about how I became a PyLady?" /><published>2020-11-01T17:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-11-01T17:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/inspiration/pyladies/2020/11/01/becoming-a-pylady</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/inspiration/pyladies/2020/11/01/becoming-a-pylady.html">&lt;h2&gt;Stepping into the Python community&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In spring 2019 I was ready for change. I was tired of learning alone after spending way too much time
    participating online courses about data, visualisation and machine learning. It was time to step out
    and pick up a challenge. At my workplace we had Lunch &amp; Learn now and then, an occasion where everybody
    who wanted could present a topic, while the rest were eating their wrap or salad. I presented an introduction
    to machine learning (ML) with a decision tree example. ML was and is still one of my major interest but I
    didn’t use it in my actual work as a software programmer.&lt;br&gt;
    The presentation went very well and I received a lot of feedback and tips what to explore next. It even lead
    through an internal project where we were using an ML algorithm for data classification, that I was leading.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Before my talk I joined PyLadies, a non-binary mentorship group for Python programmers and thought I could give a
    similar presentation there. I reached out to Éléonore who was organising events regularly to know if this would
    be a topic of interest. I had recently joined PyLadies and really liked the atmosphere of respect, curiosity
    and allowing members to try things out.
After the presentation the Éléonore asked me if I wanted to arrange similar events in the future and without
    thinking I answered “Yes sure, why not?!&quot;. I didn’t know how to do that and what that means. However I had
    a lot of trust that I would get the support that I needed.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Easy as that, suddenly I was in. And since then I organised events and had the goal to meet at least once a month.
    During events I got asked by speakers that wanted to present and contacted companies that were interested in
    hosting those kind of events, so there was always an event up in the pipeline. I got very glad when there were
    new PyLadies joining the organising team, so that we can do more in the future.
Through my work with PyLadies I also got in contact with PyCon Sweden, a non-profit organisation arranging an
    annual conference for the Python community in Sweden. The organiser team has a very welcoming group culture,
    where people decide which tasks and responsibilities they want to take over. Members get a lot of trust and
    freedom in doing their tasks. This year I joined for the second time and I was picking up new tasks and took
    more ownership, which makes me feel even more involved in the local Python community.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With the pandemic situations limiting the options to meet up most events have moved online. Since we don’t have the
    natural way of meeting and chatting at PyLadies I am now reaching out to persons that I know have something
    interesting to present.
To adapt to that new situation and continue organising the events and keep the atmosphere of learning and exploring
    I explored with the concept of the “PyLadies Online Mingle” where we can talk about ideas, tech and whatever
    comes in mind. At one of those events I found one brave member alias magicandcode who wanted to give a talk and
    Alexandra who is currently organising a study group for data analysis in Python.
So I have high hopes that we will continue with interesting and engaging events online at least until we are able
    to run face-to-face events again.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you want to give a presentation at PyLadies Stockholm, feel free to reach out to me.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All the best,
Christine
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Stepping into the Python community In spring 2019 I was ready for change. I was tired of learning alone after spending way too much time participating online courses about data, visualisation and machine learning. It was time to step out and pick up a challenge. At my workplace we had Lunch &amp; Learn now and then, an occasion where everybody who wanted could present a topic, while the rest were eating their wrap or salad. I presented an introduction to machine learning (ML) with a decision tree example. ML was and is still one of my major interest but I didn’t use it in my actual work as a software programmer. The presentation went very well and I received a lot of feedback and tips what to explore next. It even lead through an internal project where we were using an ML algorithm for data classification, that I was leading. Before my talk I joined PyLadies, a non-binary mentorship group for Python programmers and thought I could give a similar presentation there. I reached out to Éléonore who was organising events regularly to know if this would be a topic of interest. I had recently joined PyLadies and really liked the atmosphere of respect, curiosity and allowing members to try things out. After the presentation the Éléonore asked me if I wanted to arrange similar events in the future and without thinking I answered “Yes sure, why not?!&quot;. I didn’t know how to do that and what that means. However I had a lot of trust that I would get the support that I needed. Easy as that, suddenly I was in. And since then I organised events and had the goal to meet at least once a month. During events I got asked by speakers that wanted to present and contacted companies that were interested in hosting those kind of events, so there was always an event up in the pipeline. I got very glad when there were new PyLadies joining the organising team, so that we can do more in the future. Through my work with PyLadies I also got in contact with PyCon Sweden, a non-profit organisation arranging an annual conference for the Python community in Sweden. The organiser team has a very welcoming group culture, where people decide which tasks and responsibilities they want to take over. Members get a lot of trust and freedom in doing their tasks. This year I joined for the second time and I was picking up new tasks and took more ownership, which makes me feel even more involved in the local Python community. With the pandemic situations limiting the options to meet up most events have moved online. Since we don’t have the natural way of meeting and chatting at PyLadies I am now reaching out to persons that I know have something interesting to present. To adapt to that new situation and continue organising the events and keep the atmosphere of learning and exploring I explored with the concept of the “PyLadies Online Mingle” where we can talk about ideas, tech and whatever comes in mind. At one of those events I found one brave member alias magicandcode who wanted to give a talk and Alexandra who is currently organising a study group for data analysis in Python. So I have high hopes that we will continue with interesting and engaging events online at least until we are able to run face-to-face events again. If you want to give a presentation at PyLadies Stockholm, feel free to reach out to me. All the best, Christine</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An Ice Cube about Slow Multitasking</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/inspiration/mindset/2020/10/20/inspiration-slowmultitasking.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Ice Cube about Slow Multitasking" /><published>2020-10-20T19:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-10-20T19:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/inspiration/mindset/2020/10/20/inspiration-slowmultitasking</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/inspiration/mindset/2020/10/20/inspiration-slowmultitasking.html">&lt;h2&gt;An Ice Cube about Slow Multitasking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Recently I discovered a
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ted.com/talks/tim_harford_a_powerful_way_to_unleash_your_natural_creativity/transcript&quot;&gt;
        TED talk
    &lt;/a&gt;
    by Tim Harford that inspired me. He explains the concept of slow
    multitasking as a creative tool. In a nutshell it is working on different projects over a long period
    of time. The projects could go on for weeks, months, years depending on how much time they need to be
    finished. Some never finish and that is also okay.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    I love this concept! My whole life I was struggling to limit my interests because I though you can only be
    good at something if I focus on it fully. The way ordinary careers are structured by finishing school,
    selecting a profession and pursuing one path until retirement always freaked me out. I wanted to see life in a
    continuous exploration. Throughout my studies and later my work days I had a lot of ideas and interests
    popping up in my head. I thought I could become a piano player, a painter, a photographer, a surfer, a writer
    or a machine learning pioneer. I wanted to be everything but I stopped exploring the sideways because I thought
    these activities would be misleading and stealing time from my actual tasks that I have to do to become a better
    developer.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Life is not limited to one career path and a job title. With the concept of slow multitasking I no longer feel
    like have to limit myself and instead I can can allocate time and energy for projects I am interested in.
    My best example is this blog. Because for being creative it is not important
    if you think about doing one certain thing the rest of your life. Instead it is important that you start doing
    something in the first place and let your passion drive you on the way.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Think about it. What will your passion project be for the next weeks? And why don't just start today?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    All the best,
    &lt;br&gt;
    Christine
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">An Ice Cube about Slow Multitasking Recently I discovered a TED talk by Tim Harford that inspired me. He explains the concept of slow multitasking as a creative tool. In a nutshell it is working on different projects over a long period of time. The projects could go on for weeks, months, years depending on how much time they need to be finished. Some never finish and that is also okay. I love this concept! My whole life I was struggling to limit my interests because I though you can only be good at something if I focus on it fully. The way ordinary careers are structured by finishing school, selecting a profession and pursuing one path until retirement always freaked me out. I wanted to see life in a continuous exploration. Throughout my studies and later my work days I had a lot of ideas and interests popping up in my head. I thought I could become a piano player, a painter, a photographer, a surfer, a writer or a machine learning pioneer. I wanted to be everything but I stopped exploring the sideways because I thought these activities would be misleading and stealing time from my actual tasks that I have to do to become a better developer. Life is not limited to one career path and a job title. With the concept of slow multitasking I no longer feel like have to limit myself and instead I can can allocate time and energy for projects I am interested in. My best example is this blog. Because for being creative it is not important if you think about doing one certain thing the rest of your life. Instead it is important that you start doing something in the first place and let your passion drive you on the way. Think about it. What will your passion project be for the next weeks? And why don't just start today? All the best, Christine</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An Ice Cube about Grit</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/inspiration/mindset/2020/10/20/inspiration-grit.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Ice Cube about Grit" /><published>2020-10-20T18:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-10-20T18:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/inspiration/mindset/2020/10/20/inspiration-grit</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/inspiration/mindset/2020/10/20/inspiration-grit.html">&lt;h2&gt;An Ice Cube about Grit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Programming is a challenge for the mind. Not only because of the complexity of systems or features we are building,
    but also because of the setup. Most people program alone and that not always by choice. Many teams
    I have seen split up problems into smaller tasks that get implemented by one person each. The idea seems nice.
    We have a lot of work and by the divide and conquer approach we work faster towards the common goal.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    The drawback of this setup is, that this follows a lot of alone time with focus on getting thoughts into code.
    With code comes bugs and with more bugs and more code comes more and more frustration.
    And frustration was never known to be a constructive driver for qualitative programming but rather nourishes
    self-doubt. Like a tiny voice telling us that we are an imposter, that we are not as smart as our peers and
    should have become travel bloggers instead of a developers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Heads up, many of us have been there too. And will end up there again.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    But what to do?
    How do we stay on the problem anyway, find the cause of bugs or continue
    coding until everything work as we want it and not just throw the towel into the ring?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Recently I stumbled over Angela Duckworth’s TED talk about GRIT. She studies the reason that makes people successful and why.
    Are there common patterns that apply to those people?
    What do they do differently than others?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    She found out that there is a relation of talent, effort and skill.
    With an initial talent we need less effort to learn a certain skill, but if we put a lot of effort into
    learning, talent can be outperformed. The motivation to go the extra mile and put effort into improvement
    she describes as grit, the combination of passion and perseverance, the will to push forward to become better.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Isn't that great news?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    I found her description of grit inspiring, because it destroys the finality of learning and its dependency
    on talent. The brain is plastic. It has the ability to adapt and change. So, if you have a vision of your
    goal and spend the energy to progress and improve you will go further and further and improve your skill.
    &lt;br&gt;
    Programming is a skill like any other. With enough time and a curious mind, you will master it and fix the bugs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Keep that in mind when frustration is building up again and you feel like giving up.
    It's yet another step on the way to the solution and you will learn a lot from this experience.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Check out Angela Duckworth's
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ted.com/talks/angela_lee_duckworth_grit_the_power_of_passion_and_perseverance?nolanguage=en%EF%BB%BF&quot;&gt;
    TED Talk
    &lt;/a&gt;
    or the
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.econtalk.org/angela-duckworth-on-grit/&quot;&gt;
        conversation on EconTalks with Ross Roberts.
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    All the best,
    &lt;br&gt;
    Christine
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">An Ice Cube about Grit Programming is a challenge for the mind. Not only because of the complexity of systems or features we are building, but also because of the setup. Most people program alone and that not always by choice. Many teams I have seen split up problems into smaller tasks that get implemented by one person each. The idea seems nice. We have a lot of work and by the divide and conquer approach we work faster towards the common goal. The drawback of this setup is, that this follows a lot of alone time with focus on getting thoughts into code. With code comes bugs and with more bugs and more code comes more and more frustration. And frustration was never known to be a constructive driver for qualitative programming but rather nourishes self-doubt. Like a tiny voice telling us that we are an imposter, that we are not as smart as our peers and should have become travel bloggers instead of a developers. Heads up, many of us have been there too. And will end up there again. But what to do? How do we stay on the problem anyway, find the cause of bugs or continue coding until everything work as we want it and not just throw the towel into the ring? Recently I stumbled over Angela Duckworth’s TED talk about GRIT. She studies the reason that makes people successful and why. Are there common patterns that apply to those people? What do they do differently than others? She found out that there is a relation of talent, effort and skill. With an initial talent we need less effort to learn a certain skill, but if we put a lot of effort into learning, talent can be outperformed. The motivation to go the extra mile and put effort into improvement she describes as grit, the combination of passion and perseverance, the will to push forward to become better. Isn't that great news? I found her description of grit inspiring, because it destroys the finality of learning and its dependency on talent. The brain is plastic. It has the ability to adapt and change. So, if you have a vision of your goal and spend the energy to progress and improve you will go further and further and improve your skill. Programming is a skill like any other. With enough time and a curious mind, you will master it and fix the bugs. Keep that in mind when frustration is building up again and you feel like giving up. It's yet another step on the way to the solution and you will learn a lot from this experience. Check out Angela Duckworth's TED Talk or the conversation on EconTalks with Ross Roberts. All the best, Christine</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to Ice Cubes!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/welcome/intro/2020/10/18/welcome-to-ice-cubes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to Ice Cubes!" /><published>2020-10-18T13:54:49+02:00</published><updated>2020-10-18T13:54:49+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/welcome/intro/2020/10/18/welcome-to-ice-cubes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/welcome/intro/2020/10/18/welcome-to-ice-cubes.html">&lt;h2&gt;Hej! And welcome on Ice Cubes!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    My name is Christine, a software developer who besides coding in Python
    likes to make puns on her last name (Winter).
   &lt;br&gt;
    As an ambivert I also enjoy organising tech events like
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetup.com/PyLadiesStockholm/&quot;&gt;PyLadies Sthlm&lt;/a&gt;
    and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pycon.se&quot;&gt;PyCon Sweden&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    I care about the people I meet and work with. Therefore I always want to
    create an atmosphere where everybody feels welcomed and connected.
    In that way we can have interesting discussions and pick up exciting
    challenges together. And most of all, we will celebrate our successes
    as well as learn new skills on the way and grow as people.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    With this page I want to inspire you who might be interested in tech and
    just leak a bit of tools to get started. I hope you find some inspiring
    project ideas to learn tech in a fun way.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Again a very warm welcome and if you have any topic that you want me
    to cover, feel free to reach out via the contact form or email.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    All the best,
    &lt;br&gt;
    Christine
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Hej! And welcome on Ice Cubes! My name is Christine, a software developer who besides coding in Python likes to make puns on her last name (Winter). As an ambivert I also enjoy organising tech events like PyLadies Sthlm and PyCon Sweden. I care about the people I meet and work with. Therefore I always want to create an atmosphere where everybody feels welcomed and connected. In that way we can have interesting discussions and pick up exciting challenges together. And most of all, we will celebrate our successes as well as learn new skills on the way and grow as people. With this page I want to inspire you who might be interested in tech and just leak a bit of tools to get started. I hope you find some inspiring project ideas to learn tech in a fun way. Again a very warm welcome and if you have any topic that you want me to cover, feel free to reach out via the contact form or email. All the best, Christine</summary></entry></feed>